<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sett Wai</title>
    <link>https://sett.sh/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sett Wai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sw00&#34;&gt;Sett Wai&lt;/a&gt; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 15:43:11 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://sett.sh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Four principles from four people (part 1)</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/09/four-principles-from-four-people-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 15:43:11 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/09/four-principles-from-four-people-part-1/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been extremely privileged to have worked with so many different people, in so many different contexts. Being exposed to such diversity has greatly benefited me and enriched my world view. But there&amp;rsquo;s also a little bit of everyone I&amp;rsquo;ve internalised - little tools, values and principles for which I am grateful.
You get to learn a lot about a person just by pairing with them on a technical problem or even collaborating on something more strategic1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical failure and the mechanics of causality</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/08/critical-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 17:46:57 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/08/critical-failure/</guid>
      <description>The biggest critical failure that I&amp;rsquo;ve ever experienced on a project happened on the first week of 2014 and caused a recurring outage that lasted a full four days.
It was my very first large-scale, distributed production system with multi-national integrations and a real-time messaging component. I had been on the project for 3 months and had inherited the tech lead role which I shared with a senior colleague who had joined after me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sublime Tool</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/08/the-sublime-tool/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2018 19:23:38 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/08/the-sublime-tool/</guid>
      <description>This was initially meant to be a technical post like I promised, but I was faced with several dilemmas:
 Any particular tech I write about will be obsolete by next Tuesday, the standard unit of time it takes for unlikely events to occur in computing.. There will always be much better resources elsewhere, because I&amp;rsquo;m not an expert in anything.  So instead of yet another tutorial on test-driven Ansible, Kafka or whatever the hottest web framework of the week, I present to you some great ideas that have a better shelf-life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dude, where&#39;s my flow?</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/08/dude-wheres-my-flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/08/dude-wheres-my-flow/</guid>
      <description>Or, In Which Sett Loses His Shit.
Toward the end of last year I realised had lost the ability to focus. To compound matters, I was in a position where focus wasn&amp;rsquo;t really required of me - I was tech lead, but in this case my resposibilities had drifted from the concerns of technical delivery and all of my energy was spent solely on trying to sort signal from noise1. Needless to say, it was an astronomically dysfunctional and frustrating environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On dilettantism, craft and mastery</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/07/on-dilettantism-craft-and-mastery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2018/07/on-dilettantism-craft-and-mastery/</guid>
      <description>Hello, world. It&amp;rsquo;s been a while. There are some words that I&amp;rsquo;ve been holding on to that I&amp;rsquo;d like to set free. I&amp;rsquo;ve also been hiding somewhat and now taking some tentative steps back into the light. This is the first meager step. I have some more to follow. Please be gentle and patient with me.
For continuity, I&amp;rsquo;ve cross-posted my last public appearance here.
I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a generalist. And this has served me well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four years, infinite gratitude</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2017/12/four-years-infinite-gratitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2017/12/four-years-infinite-gratitude/</guid>
      <description>This is a cross-post of my original Facebook note, announcing my decision to exit TW and tech to take a break.
San Antonio, Kampala, Porto Alegre, San Francisco, Nairobi, Johannesburg. These are the cities I have worked in during my time at ThoughtWorks (TW), that quirky (yet “elite”) global IT consultancy that Martin Fowler works for, little known outside of tech circles. Needless to say, I am the most privileged person I know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker for Windows Users</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/docker-for-windows-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/docker-for-windows-users/</guid>
      <description>As with many people my age (27), I primarily started working and playing on computers when graphical user interfaces were already the norm and Windows 95 had just hit the peak of popularity. Unless your parents were engineers of some sort, personal computers were generally seen as just a new home appliance. If you had a computer in the 90s, it most likely was a Packard Bell that came with Windows 95 and Intel Pentium processor of some sort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A day in Gramado</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/day-in-gramado/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/day-in-gramado/</guid>
      <description>Last Saturday three of my colleagues and I embarked on a day trip to the odd, little town of Gramado, Rio Grande du Sol.
2h 11min is a lie! Does not include time getting inexplicably lost.
You only need to drive about an hour towards Nova Petrópolis to understand why that particular area of Brazil is so odd. From the moment you leave the industrial cities of São Leopoldo and Novo Hamburgo1 the landscape changes drastically, revealing lush green, forested hills and meandering roads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributing to Pixelated</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/contributing-to-pixelated/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/contributing-to-pixelated/</guid>
      <description>Last week the pixelated team here in TW Porto Alegre hosted a hack night which allowed me to dive into the enigmatic Pixelated Project and even submit a pull request! Read on if you&amp;rsquo;d like to know more.
The majority of the world&amp;rsquo;s emails are hosted at large, centralised providers. Let&amp;rsquo;s face it, there is practically no substitute for Gmail and in light of the Snowden Revelations we&amp;rsquo;ve willingly sacrificed our privacy for convenience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Easter in POA</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/easter-in-poa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/posts/2015/04/easter-in-poa/</guid>
      <description>I had finally arrived in Porto Alegre on Tuesday night after approximately a 16 hour trip(transit via GRU). A quick 15 minute taxi ride took me to neighbourhood of Bom Fim, where I&amp;rsquo;d be staying in a hotel until more permanent living arrangements were made. Marcelo, my cab driver was a helpful guy and offered a lot of advice and information about the city as we drove through it. I was too bewildered and tired to take note of any of it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>