<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sett Wai</title>
    <link>https://sett.sh/tags/personal/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sett Wai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sw00&#34;&gt;Sett Wai&lt;/a&gt; 2016</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://sett.sh/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A day in Gramado</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/post/day-in-gramado/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/post/day-in-gramado/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday three of my colleagues and I embarked on a day trip to the odd, little town of Gramado, Rio Grande du Sol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/4mshU4Ml.png&#34; alt=&#34;Google map of trip&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;2h 11min is a lie! Does not include time getting inexplicably lost.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You only need to drive about an hour towards Nova Petrópolis to understand why that particular area of Brazil is so odd. From the moment you leave the industrial cities of São Leopoldo and Novo Hamburgo&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:cities&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:cities&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the landscape changes drastically, revealing lush green, forested hills and meandering roads. It seems like a totally different country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a pit stop in Nova Petrópolis at a cafè that could just as well have been in some secluded German village&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:europe&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:europe&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. There was even a village fare taking place across the road. Oh! The roads! The roads had roundabouts with well tendered flowers in them and pedestrian crossings that cars would dilligently obey. But these were only tiny omens of things to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/9HfNwIml.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Nova Petropolis&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Am I in Nova Petrólpolis or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0780536/&#34;&gt;in Bruges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/5X9XbhEl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Nova Petropolis&#34; /&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Some sort of monument to Monty Python, I think.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll know when you enter Gramado because the air itself seems different (I sweat it&amp;rsquo;s freshly imported from the Alps or something). Also everything will look like something out of a fairytale and the restaurant prices will skyrocket&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:caro&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:caro&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - expect fondue and eisbein instead of the usual &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Churrasco&#34;&gt;churrasco&lt;/a&gt; here. Finally, there&amp;rsquo;ll also be a massive gantry of stone with &amp;ldquo;Gramado&amp;rdquo; written on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/JGNTSMBl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Gantry when entering Gramado&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Another tribute monument to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A8yjNbcKkNY&#34;&gt;Monty Python and the Holy Grail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The town presents itself as an idyllic european village where the rich spend their weekends and retire to. We actually spent some time driving around, following a vintage red bus that was showing tourists all the wonderful private property that could be found in the village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/qHqmrztl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Private Home in Gramado&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Someone&amp;rsquo;s humble abode.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gramado is also the home of Mini Mundo, a theme park featuring miniature replicas of monuments and a generic European village with a train track. It also has some stores full of overpriced ceramic curios, perfect gifts for retirees in an old age home. And just for the younglings, there are some terrifying figures of anthropomorphic rabbits and depications of medieval village life&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:holidays&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:holidays&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/s25KOWel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Peter Rabbit&#39;s family&#34; /&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Peter Rabbit&amp;rsquo;s family&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/gL1LDMtl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Medieval matron potty training a kid&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Medieval matron potty training a kid. Also, sign for the banheiros(bathrooms).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/ZNNdrcCl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Mini Mundo&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Small World&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lagos-negro-the-black-lake&#34;&gt;Lagos Negro: The Black Lake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next attraction simply deserved it&amp;rsquo;s own spooky title. Lagos Negro. The Black Lake. I spotted it on a sign during our drive through the village and was compelled to see this&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:lagos-negro&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:lagos-negro&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lake itself was quite small and not as dark and foreboding as I&amp;rsquo;d hoped. What was interesting is that it is actually situated on a hill. Of course it would have some paddle boats shaped as swans &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:paddle-boats&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:paddle-boats&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and surrounded by pristine vegetation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/tH5mA7El.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Resorts by the lake&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Lakeside resorts&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/wEKJdM7l.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Swan Paddle boats&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Paddle boats&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;canela-cathederal-and-parque-caracol&#34;&gt;Canela: Cathederal and Parque Caracol&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 10 minutes further out of Gramado, you&amp;rsquo;ll encounter the town of Canela (it means cinnamon in Portuguese). Although it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to know when Gramado actually ends and Canela begins, the latter actually sports its own tourist attractions: a stone cathedral in the village center and Caracol Parque, a large park featuring a beautiful valley with a waterfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/DMXHPL4l.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cathedral of Our Lady of Lourdes&#34; /&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Cathedral of Our Lady of Lourdes a.k.a. Cathedral of Stone - my first visit to a gothic Cathedral!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/hotRgh6l.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cathedral interior&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, a distinctly English Gothic cathedral is quite an unusual sight to see in Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/HQo0dsOl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Caracol Parque&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Map of Caracol Parque&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parque Caracol (Snail Park) features a beautiful valley and is one the main attractions in Canela. There are several view points and even a cable cart. We were there to see the waterfall however, and (carefully) walked the thousand or so steps down to the bottom. It was a wonderful way to end the day (although the walk back up almost killed us).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/cPApFMcl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Steps down to the waterfall in Parque Caracol&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Over a thousand steps! A lot more treacherous and steep in real life.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/FJP1lkil.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Waterfall&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Cascada!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/Hw1PM4El.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A critter on the steps&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;This little critter bumbled passed me obviously on an important critter mission.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot other awesome attractions in Canela we never got to visit. I wish we had skipped Gramado completely for Canela, because we passed several awesome looking amusement parks there we never got to visit. Including one with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2LX0jWKbTpc&#34;&gt;mechanical life-size dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it&amp;rsquo;s well worth visiting this oddball part of Rio Grande even if it&amp;rsquo;s a bit tourist-y. It&amp;rsquo;s got beautiful landscapes and a pleasant maritime climate. I imagine this is where Brazilians go to visit foreign place without actually leaving the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That evening we had dinner at this crazy place back in Canela that gives you an all you can eat smorgasbord of food for only 35 reais.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/bEBZHr2l.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lots of food&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Ridiculous amount of food.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/1TgqrbLl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Red house&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Random red house&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/aZDijFsl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Animals playing instruments&#34; /&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Remember this fable? Stuff of nightmares&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/nNtMyyql.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Rabbits&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;No, no, there is no escape from Easter here.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:cities&#34;&gt;Smaller industrial cities just outside of Porto Alegre - we passed through them en route to Gramado. The road is a straight 3 lane highway through them. You already start seeing the Euro influence in Novo Hamburg (New Hamburg!?)
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:cities&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:europe&#34;&gt;I have actually never been to Europe. But I assume this is exactly how I imagine it. And I reckon residents of Nova Petrópolis and Gramado imagine it to be the same as everything seems to be carefully constructed to reflect that vision.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:europe&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:caro&#34;&gt;We made the mistake of eating at the 2nd resaturant we found because we were starving (1st was unaffordable at 80 reais per person, 2nd was still expensive). I recommend you pack a lunch, or find a food stall near the Lagos Negro park.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:caro&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:holidays&#34;&gt;Gramado is a hotspot during Easter and Christmas, the cheery residents love it so much they celebrate them for the entire month. Incidentally, acommodation prices hike up during those times too.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:holidays&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:lagos-negro&#34;&gt;At first the name, understandibly, puzzled my two friends who are from Uganda and Nigeria.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:lagos-negro&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:paddle-boats&#34;&gt;Every body of water I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered so far that&amp;rsquo;s bigger than a puddle seems to have these things.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:paddle-boats&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Easter in POA</title>
      <link>https://sett.sh/post/easter-in-poa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sett.sh/post/easter-in-poa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had finally arrived in Porto Alegre on Tuesday night after approximately a 16 hour trip(transit via &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S%C3%A3o_Paulo-Guarulhos_International_Airport&#34;&gt;GRU&lt;/a&gt;). A quick 15 minute taxi ride took me to neighbourhood of Bom Fim, where I&amp;rsquo;d be staying in a hotel until more permanent living arrangements were made. Marcelo, my cab driver was a helpful guy and offered a lot of advice and information about the city as we drove through it. I was too bewildered and tired to take note of any of it. I noticed main roads used a two way system with a bus lane in the middle. He apologised as we passed through some district where there was &amp;ldquo;bad bars and prostitutes&amp;rdquo; (as he put it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking out upon the city skyline and streets in the day quickly dispelled all notions of the Brazil I&amp;rsquo;d imagined from its portrayals in pop culture. I have worked with a few wonderful Brazilian colleagues in Johannesburg and  even though I knew that the colourful and gritty Brazil portrayed in the likes of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0317248/&#34;&gt;City of God&lt;/a&gt; is at best a caricature of only one city, there is always some romanticised attachment to the clichès and perspectives of the imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/IvB2rBBl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;POA Skyline from hotel elevator&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Lots of little apartment buildings in Bom Fim.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city of Porto Alegre is situated in the state of Rio Grande du Sol (Big River of the South) and is known for having a very European vibe to it. There are still lot of old buildings down town though most of them are left as facades for parking or some other modern use behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The streets look clean to me but for the abundance of graffiti ranging from small murals to more common &amp;ldquo;tags&amp;rdquo;. You will not find the grit and chaos of Bree street here&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. You will instead find giant, ancient &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacaranda&#34;&gt;Jacaranda&lt;/a&gt; trees covered in beautiful vines. Which totally messed with my perception of where I am since I grew up in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://showme.co.za/pretoria/tourism/the-jacaranda-city/&#34;&gt;Jacaranda City&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/K1StkTil.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Giant Jacarandas in POA&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Wait, am I back home?&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be quite honest I do not know much of the history of Brazil, let alone Porto Alegre (POA for short) but I hope to discover more in my year-long adventure here. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the lesser known cities despite having hosted a world cup match&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I had in fact not heard of it before meeting coworkers who hailed from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I did find out is that it&amp;rsquo;s right next a big river that makes it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com.br/maps/@-30.0503783,-51.1901651,11z?hl=en&#34;&gt;look like a bay&lt;/a&gt; in Google Maps. And then I found out the the river I was looking at is actually a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com.br/maps/@-30.5023817,-51.1357736,9z?hl=en&#34;&gt;small part of a HUGE river&lt;/a&gt;. POA is situated on the edge of fractal!! And &amp;ldquo;Big River of the South&amp;rdquo; needs a better name like &amp;ldquo;MASSIVE river of the South&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Rio Godzilla du Sol&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/W9yTSP9l.png&#34; alt=&#34;Map of Porto Alegre&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Cool, it&amp;rsquo;s a bay!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/5CaqxVMl.png&#34; alt=&#34;Map of Porto Alegre zoomed out&#34; title=&#34;Rio Godzilla du Sol&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Oh. Hang on&amp;hellip;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://wikitravel.org/en/Porto_Alegre&#34;&gt;WikiTravel&lt;/a&gt; page is shorter than most destinations, its biggest feature being its parks. And boy, are the parks plentiful and beautiful. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farroupilha_Park&#34;&gt;Parque Farroupilha&lt;/a&gt; was a short walking distance away from our hotel so my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/amukizaa&#34;&gt;Andrew&lt;/a&gt; and I decided to brave a walk and maybe get some lunch on the way. It turns out this is a difficult thing to do on Good Friday since all the usual restaurants are closed and we don&amp;rsquo;t speak Portuguese. We settled on some hot dog &amp;ldquo;especial&amp;rdquo; from a food truck next to the park and much awkard gesturing and sheepish &amp;ldquo;sim&amp;rdquo;s and &amp;ldquo;obrigados&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It was more than a hot dog, the man layered a dozen sauces and stuff on top of it such that it could pass as modern art. And it was delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough of this deliberation, have some photos from that walk:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/UDk2BIil.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Awesome mural painting on what&#39;s presumably a hot dog and chips joint when it&#39;s open.&#34; title=&#34;Fast food surrealism!&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;When fast food attacks!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/HfeE8myl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Posters for an anti capitalism protest&#34; title=&#34;Anti Capitalismo Protest!&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Anti Capitalismo Proteste! I like this place already.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/1mCW6Swl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Abacaxi truck&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Abacaxi is the &amp;ldquo;cellar door&amp;rdquo; of the Portuguese language, except it actually makes sense.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/R1283WGl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tortoise and Swan&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Tortoise and Swan.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day we enlisted the help our Bolivian colleague who had been living in POA for around 3 years now. She knew the area and Portuguese (although she says it&amp;rsquo;s difficult, being a native Spanish speaker herself&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). We went back to the Parque Farroupilha for a longer walk without the edge of not being able to communicate and then we went down town to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porto_Alegre_Public_Market&#34;&gt;Mercado Público&lt;/a&gt;, a big old building in the city centre with dozens of stalls selling stuff from curios to meat and cheese. Unfortunately I didn&amp;rsquo;t snap any pictures from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that we went to Praça da Alfândega nearby which had MARGS (Museum of Art) near it. Now MARGS is free to enter and has a permanent collection with some peripharel exhibitions sometimes. It had a lot contemporary pieces but the most amazing work I saw was the painting below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/5VYtrrQl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Emigrante&amp;quot; painting&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a portrait of an immigrant by a Napoleone Grady, an Italian artist, painted in 1887. Every now and then you see a painting that has some ineffable, metaphysical property - you can swear by it. This was one of those. Looking at it for a few moments, you could hear the waves in the background and the same impossible light that you find in Rembrandt&amp;rsquo;s paintings illuminating the lady. I would definitely like to go back and view it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, to contrast the previous day&amp;rsquo;s high cultural experiences I joined some of my new colleagues who were attending an Anime convention. I don&amp;rsquo;t think it needs much explanation than the photos below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/l3BhYHAl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Crowd inside Anime Convention&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;More cosplayers than casuals.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/Y7QqR3ol.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Excellent costume&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Award winning costume.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/sDJVrAKl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Girls with big guns&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Obligatory girls with big guns who later turned out to be the judges of the cosplay competition.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anime enthusiasts, geeks, nerds etc&amp;hellip; in POA seem to take cosplay very seriously, as evidenced by the quality of costumes and props. What struck me is that despite being a relatively small convention (I estimate only about 500 people there), there were more people dressed in costume than not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, my first weekend in Brazil has been very surprising and a lot of fun. I&amp;rsquo;m currently trying to learn more Portuguese and enjoying my time here. Happy belated Easter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/kdORFIvl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Street Art in the Park&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Murals at Parque Farroupilha.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/y3nT3k7l.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Amazing sculpture from entrance of MARGS&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Amazing unmarked sculpture at the entrance of MARGS&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/qGsc2zFl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Doctor Who stall at Anime Convetion&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;A stall for every fandom.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Bree street is in Johannesburgs&amp;rsquo; CBD (Central Building District, or Downtown) and has a very post-apocalyptic feeling to it because of it&amp;rsquo;s crumbling, abandoned buildings and trash everywhere. I drove through it at night a few times and navigating it is difficult, often having to avoid the odd piece of furniture on the road and disorganised side streets.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Marcelo, my cab driver from the airport, pointed out some roadworks that had been underway since before the World Cup and still has not been completed. Some 	roads were still closed.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Sim = yes, obrigado = thank you (male). Incidentally these will be the most spoken sounds you make when in your first week in Brazil.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Brazil is the only Portuguese speaking country in South America. This is okay because it is also the biggest country on the continent.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>